<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:space="preserve" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ZERO IMPACT AI-DRIVEN FOOD REDISTRIBUTION SYSTEM FOR SUSTAINABLE WASTE REDUCTION</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ebonica Saleth</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Head of the Department</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Kingston Engineering College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vellore</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Balaji</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yashema</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Akshaya</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Kingston Engineering College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vellore</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Student</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ZERO IMPACT AI-DRIVEN FOOD REDISTRIBUTION SYSTEM FOR SUSTAINABLE WASTE REDUCTION</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F26A93697B1FC2B3E037865417A3A51C</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2026-03-09T18:03+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Food waste</term>
					<term>AI</term>
					<term>sustainability</term>
					<term>blockchain</term>
					<term>zero impact</term>
					<term>circular economy</term>
					<term>food security</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper presents an innovative zero-impact AI-driven food redistribution system that tackles the pressing issues of food waste and hunger in our communities. By combining smart technology with environmental consciousness, our system connects surplus food from restaurants, supermarkets, and cafeterias with people and organizations in need, all while producing zero environmental harm. During a six-month pilot trial across three metropolitan areas, our AIdriven system enabled participating businesses to reduce measured food waste by 78%. A total of 112 tons of edible surplus food were redistributed, based on real-time system tracking logs. Analysis of this redistribution, using standard greenhouse gas conversion factors, showed the prevention of approximately 203 metric tons of CO₂ equivalent emissions. Our approach-powered by renewable energy and balanced through carbon offsetting-creates a new standard for sustainable food redistribution. This research offers a practical, scalable solution that can work in various communities and economic settings to address both environmental and social challenges.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ijrti.org/">www.ijrti.org</ref>) d190</p><p>2. Develop a carbon-neutral framework for all operational aspects 3. Measure how effectively the system reduces food waste, helps feed people in need, and minimizes environmental impact 4. Determine whether the system can work in different communities and settings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. LITERATURE REVIEW Food Waste and Environmental Impact</head><p>Food waste isn't just about the food itself-it represents wasted resources throughout the food chain. Conrad et al. <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref> found that producing food that eventually gets thrown away consumes about 24% of the world's freshwater and 23% of global farmland. Makov et al. <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref> showed that food waste contributes to biodiversity loss by requiring more land for agriculture and causing pollution from fertilizers and pesticides. The climate impact is especially concerning. Zhang and Patel <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref> calculated that if food waste were a country, it would be the third-largest greenhouse gas emitter after China and the United States. These emissions come from every stage of the food's life-from farming and processing to transportation and decomposition in landfills.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Existing Food Redistribution Systems</head><p>Food redistribution has evolved in recent years. Reynolds et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[7]</ref> documented how food banks have started using digital platforms to improve their operations. However, even with these improvements, Liu and Johnson <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[8]</ref> found that digitallyequipped food banks still waste about 20% of donated food because they can't coordinate pickup, storage, and delivery effectively. Food-sharing apps have emerged as another solution. Eriksson and Brown <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[9]</ref> studied these apps in European cities and found that while they successfully diverted food from landfills, they only worked well in densely populated areas and often excluded people without smartphones or reliable internet access. Many of these apps also prioritize convenience over environmental concerns, sometimes increasing transportation emissions by encouraging individual trips to pick up small amounts of food.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AI Applications in Food Systems</head><p>Artificial intelligence shows great promise for food waste reduction. Nguyen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[10]</ref> developed machine learning algorithms that predicted food surplus in grocery stores with 85% accuracy. Wang and Garcia <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[11]</ref> created an AI system for planning food delivery routes that reduced transportation emissions by 34%. Blockchain technology-a secure digital record-keeping system-has also been applied to food donation. Hernandez et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[12]</ref> implemented a blockchain system for tracking food donations that increased donor participation by 45% by providing transparent records and reducing liability concerns. However, Kouhizadeh and Sarkis <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[13]</ref> pointed out that some blockchain systems consume enormous amounts of energy, potentially creating more environmental problems than they solve.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Gap</head><p>Despite these advances, there's still a need for comprehensive systems that address both the logistical challenges of food redistribution and environmental impact. Most existing solutions focus either on technology without considering their carbon footprint, or on sustainability without using advanced AI capabilities. Our research bridges this gap by creating a system that combines smart technology with truly sustainable operations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. METHODOLOGY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System Design</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System Architecture</head><p>We designed our Zero Impact AI-Driven Food Redistribution System with four main components:</p><p>1. Data Collection Layer: We installed smart sensors at participating food donor locations (restaurants, supermarkets, hotels, and cafeterias) to monitor food inventory in real-time. These sensors tracked the amount and type of food, temperature conditions, and estimated shelf life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IJRTI2504322</head><p>International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ijrti.org/">www.ijrti.org</ref>) d191</p><p>2. AI Processing Core: The heart of our system is a set of machine learning models that analyze data from the sensors to predict when and where surplus food will be available, match it with appropriate recipients, and plan the most efficient pickup and delivery routes.</p><p>3. Blockchain Verification System: We implemented a low-energy blockchain system to record every step of the process-from donation to delivery-ensuring transparency and accountability while protecting everyone's data privacy.</p><p>4. Zero-Impact Infrastructure: Our operations run on 100% renewable energy, with electric delivery vehicles, compostable packaging, energy-efficient equipment, and carbon offsets for emissions we couldn't eliminate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AI Algorithm Development</head><p>Our AI system uses three interconnected machine learning models:</p><p>1. Surplus Prediction Model: This model learns from patterns in each donor's operations to predict when they'll have surplus food 12-48 hours in advance. It considers factors like sales history, day of the week, weather, and local events.</p><p>2. Recipient Matching Algorithm: This algorithm finds the best match between available food and potential recipients based on food type, quantity, nutritional needs, location, and each organization's capacity.</p><p>3. Route Optimization Engine: This model plans the most efficient pickup and delivery routes to minimize driving distance and carbon emissions while ensuring food arrives before it spoils.</p><p>We initially trained these models on simulated data and then let them learn and improve through real world experience during the project.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blockchain Implementation</head><p>We used a special type of blockchain called Hyperledger Fabric that requires very little energy compared to cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin. The blockchain recorded every transaction-when food was donated, who verified its quality, which recipient received it, and when it was delivered. Smart contracts (automated programs on the blockchain) ensured everyone followed food safety rules and donor requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Zero-Impact Framework</head><p>We achieved carbon neutrality through:</p><p>1. Energy Efficiency: We selected the most energy-efficient computers and software for our system.</p><p>2. Renewable Energy: All our servers and electric vehicle charging stations ran on renewable energymostly solar and wind power.</p><p>3. Carbon Offsetting: For emissions we couldn't eliminate (like those from manufacturing the sensors), we purchased verified carbon offsets, primarily supporting reforestation and renewable energy projects in areas where food is grown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pilot Implementation</head><p>We tested our system in three different urban areas:</p><p>1. Metropolitan Area A: A dense city center with 78 food donors (42 restaurants, 15 supermarkets, 12 hotels, 9 cafeterias) and 23 recipient organizations (food banks, community centers, shelters).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Metropolitan Area B:</head><p>A medium-density area with 53 food donors and 18 recipient organizations.</p><p>3. Metropolitan Area C: A more suburban area with 41 food donors and 14 recipient organizations.</p><p>International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ijrti.org/">www.ijrti.org</ref>) d192</p><p>The pilot ran for six months from October 2024 to March 2025, with a month beforehand to install equipment and train participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collection</head><p>We gathered data in several ways:</p><p>1. System Performance Metrics: We automatically tracked how much food was redistributed, what types of food, how accurately we matched donors with recipients, delivery times, and energy use.</p><p>2. Environmental Impact Assessment: We calculated the emissions avoided by diverting food from landfills, the emissions from our operations, and the overall environmental impact using the EPA's WARM (Waste Reduction Model) methodology.</p><p>3. Participant Surveys: Every three months, we surveyed food donors and recipients about their experiences, challenges, and suggestions.</p><p>4. Food Waste Audits: Each month, we measured waste at donor locations to see how much they reduced compared to before joining our program.</p><p>5. Economic Analysis: We tracked operational costs, time savings, and the value of redistributed food using standardized food valuation metrics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analytical Approach</head><p>We analyzed our data using several methods:</p><p>1. Statistical Analysis: We compared food waste levels before and after implementation, identified factors that influenced system effectiveness, and looked for patterns over time.</p><p>2. Life Cycle Assessment: We conducted a comprehensive environmental impact analysis following ISO 14040/14044 standards to compare our system with traditional approaches.</p><p>3. Qualitative Analysis: We analyzed survey responses and feedback to identify common themes, challenges, and success factors.</p><p>4. Performance Benchmarking: We compared our performance metrics with established standards from research and industry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">System Performance</head><p>Our six-month pilot showed impressive results across all three metropolitan areas, as shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. All figures were derived from the system's tracking logs, which recorded each transaction from donation to delivery.</p><p>Table 1: System Performance Metrics Metric Metropolitan Area A Metropolitan Area B Metropolitan Area C Overall Total food redistributed (tons) 52.3 38.7 21.4 112.4 Average matching accuracy (%) 93.8 91.2 89.5 91.5 Average time from surplus identification to recipient matching (hours) 0.86 1.12 1.32 1.10 Average delivery time (hours) 2.3 2.7 3.1 2.7 Percentage of food donors actively participating (%) 92.3 88.7 85.4 89.0 Percentage of available surplus food successfully redistributed (%) 84.2 77.5 71.8 78.0 International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ijrti.org/">www.ijrti.org</ref>) d193</p><p>Note: Matching accuracy was determined through recipient satisfaction surveys and quality control checks. Active participation was defined as at least one donation per week during the pilot period.</p><p>Our AI prediction model demonstrated increasing accuracy throughout the pilot period, with the error rate in surplus prediction decreasing from 18.3% in the first month to just 7.2% by the sixth month. The recipient matching algorithm achieved a 91.5% satisfaction rate among recipient organizations, indicating we successfully matched food types with their needs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Environmental Impact</head><p>Our system delivered significant environmental benefits while maintaining its zero-impact goal, as shown in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>.</p><p>Table 2: Environmental Impact Metrics Metric Quantity Calculation Method Total CO₂e emissions avoided through food waste diversion (metric tons) 203.5 Based on EPA WARM model (1.8 kg CO₂e per kg food waste diverted from landfill) System operational emissions before offsetting (metric tons CO₂e) 18.3 Life cycle assessment following ISO 14040/14044 standards Carbon offsets purchased (metric tons CO₂e) 18.3 Verified Carbon Standard (VCS) certified offsets Net system carbon footprint (metric tons CO₂e) 0 Operational emissions minus offsets Water saved through avoided food production (million liters) 237.2 Based on FAO (2023) global average: 2,112 liters of water per kg of food Land use saved through avoided food production (hectares) 42.8 Based on FAO (2023) global average: 0.38 m² of land per kg of food</p><p>Note: Environmental impact calculations follow standardized methodologies. Water and land savings represent the resources that would have been needed to produce an equivalent amount of food as was redistributed.</p><p>Our life cycle assessment showed that our system reduced greenhouse gas emissions by 94.8% compared to sending food to landfills and by 62.3% compared to conventional food banks and donation programs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social Impact</head><p>Our system made a meaningful difference in addressing hunger:</p><p> Provided 420,300 meal equivalents to people in need (calculated using the USDA standard of 1.2 pounds of food per meal)  Engaged 172 volunteers in system operations and food handling  Created 14 new jobs for system management and operations  Improved the nutritional quality of food at recipient organizations, with a 32% increase in fresh produce distribution compared to pre-implementation baseline Survey results from recipient organizations indicated high satisfaction (4.6/5.0 average rating) with the system, particularly appreciating the improved consistency and quality of food compared to traditional donation methods.</p><p>International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ijrti.org/">www.ijrti.org</ref>) d194</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Economic Analysis</head><p>Our economic analysis showed benefits for different stakeholders:</p><p>For Food Donors:</p><p> Average reduction of 12.3% in waste management costs  Tax benefits from documented donations valued at approximately $684,000  Enhanced brand reputation and customer loyalty (qualitative feedback)</p><p>For Recipient Organizations:</p><p> Received food valued at an estimated $1.23 million  34% reduction in food procurement costs  22% reduction in staff time spent sourcing donations System Economics:</p><p> Total implementation cost: $412,000 (including technology, equipment, and setup)  Operational costs for six months: $183,000 (including staff, energy, maintenance, and carbon offsets)  Return on investment (ROI): 178% over the six-month period</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Innovative Features</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Community Engagement Platform</head><p>One of our most successful innovations was the Community Engagement Platform integrated into the system. This digital platform enabled:</p><p>1. Community-Powered Last-Mile Delivery: A volunteer network for short-distance deliveries using zero emission methods, reducing delivery emissions by 17%.</p><p>2. Participatory Surplus Prevention: Knowledge sharing among food donors that helped reduce overall food surplus by 14% beyond the food that was redistributed.</p><p>3. Nutrition-Focused Matching: Incorporating nutritional analysis to ensure balanced food options for recipient organizations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adaptive Food Quality Assessment</head><p>We developed an AI-powered visual recognition system that could:</p><p>1. Objectively Assess Edibility: Distinguish between cosmetic imperfections and actual food safety issues.</p><p>2. Suggest Processing Options: Recommend methods to extend usability for food nearing the end of its optimal quality. This feature increased the amount of food we could safely redistribute by an estimated 22% compared to traditional visual inspection methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System Effectiveness</head><p>Our results show that an AI-driven food redistribution system can significantly reduce food waste while maintaining zero environmental impact. Our 78% success rate in redistributing available surplus food is much better than traditional food rescue operations, which typically achieve 45-60% success rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[14]</ref>.</p><p>International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ijrti.org/">www.ijrti.org</ref>) d195</p><p>This improvement comes from three key innovations: First, our system predicts food surplus in advance rather than just reacting when it becomes available. By anticipating surplus 12-48 hours ahead of time, we can plan logistics and ensure recipients are ready.</p><p>Second, our matching algorithm ensures food goes to organizations that can actually use it. This prevents the common problem where food banks receive donations they can't properly store or distribute.</p><p>Third, our blockchain system creates trust and accountability. Several donors told us they participated specifically because they could track their donations and verify they were handled safely.</p><p>We did find that the system worked better in denser urban areas, suggesting that having more participants in a smaller geographic area improves efficiency-probably because it enables more diverse matching options and shorter delivery routes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Environmental Sustainability</head><p>Achieving zero environmental impact sets our system apart from existing approaches. Previous research by Martinez and Wong <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[15]</ref> found that conventional food rescue operations typically generate 0.2-0.5 kg of carbon dioxide equivalent (CO₂e) per kg of food redistributed through transportation, storage, and operations. Our system generated only 0.16 kg CO₂e per kg of food before offsets, and zero net emissions after offsets.</p><p>We managed transportation emissions particularly well through optimized routes and electric vehicles. However, the manufacturing of our IoT sensors remains our biggest environmental challenge, accounting for over half of our pre-offset emissions. Future versions should focus on making sensors that last longer and are produced with lower-impact materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social and Economic Implications</head><p>Beyond the environmental benefits, our system made a real difference in people's lives. Providing over 420,000 meals helps address food insecurity in our pilot communities. The improved nutritional quality-especially more fresh produce-addresses a common criticism that food donation programs often provide mostly processed, less nutritious foods.</p><p>The economic analysis shows that everyone benefits financially. Food donors save on waste disposal costs and receive tax incentives, while recipient organizations get valuable food that reduces their expenses. The positive return on investment indicates that the system can sustain itself financially while maintaining zero environmental impact.</p><p>However, the initial implementation costs could be a barrier, especially in lower-income communities. Future development should focus on reducing these costs through economies of scale and exploring partnerships between public agencies, nonprofits, and businesses to share the investment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations and Challenges</head><p>Despite our success, we identified several challenges:</p><p>1. Scalability Concerns: The system worked best in dense urban areas, raising questions about how well it would work in rural or less-populated regions.</p><p>2. Data Privacy: While our blockchain system secured data, some participants worried about sharing their operational information.</p><p>3. Technical Barriers: Smaller food donors sometimes struggled with the technology, indicating a need for simpler interfaces and better training.</p><p>4. Regulatory Variations: Different regions had different rules about food donation, requiring customized configurations of our smart contracts.</p><p>5. Participation Dependency: The system works better with more participants, highlighting the need for effective community engagement strategies.</p><p>6. Sensor Limitations: The IoT sensors sometimes struggled to accurately assess highly variable or mixed food items, requiring human verification in about 18% of cases.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Track Quality Changes Over Time: Learn how different foods deteriorate in various conditions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="2,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="3,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="4,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="5,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="7,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="9,139.80,159.00,332.20,452.00" type="bitmap"/></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">) d196 VI. CONCLUSION Our research demonstrates that a zero-impact AI-driven food redistribution system can effectively address both food waste and hunger while maintaining environmental neutrality</title>
		<ptr target="www.ijrti.org"/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Research Trends and Innovation</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Key findings include</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Integrating AI prediction, matching algorithms, and route optimization significantly improves food redistribution efficiency, achieving a 78% success rate</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Carbon-neutral operations are achievable through energy-efficient design, renewable energy</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>and targeted carbon offsetting</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Blockchain technology enhances transparency and trust without compromising environmental sustainability when implemented thoughtfully</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The system creates positive economic value for all stakeholders, suggesting potential for self sustaining operations at scale</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">System effectiveness varies with contextual factors, particularly population density and participant diversity</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Community engagement features and adaptive food quality assessment significantly enhance system effectiveness and social impact. Theoretically, our research shows how advanced technologies can be deployed without harming the environment. It challenges the assumption that technological solutions necessarily create new environmental problems, providing a model for technologyenabled sustainability initiatives</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">we offer a blueprint for implementing effective food redistribution systems that use AI capabilities while maintaining environmental integrity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Practically</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Our documented success provides evidence for policymakers, funders, and community organizations considering similar initiatives</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Long-term Studies: Extending the pilot duration to observe how the system performs over multiple seasons and years</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Rural Adaptation: Investigating how to adapt the system for effective operation in less densely populated areas</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Testing the system across diverse cultural, economic, and regulatory contexts</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cross-cultural Implementation</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Greener Sensors: Developing lower-impact IoT sensors with reduced manufacturing footprints</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Policy Integration: Exploring how systems like ours can be supported by policy frameworks at local, regional, and national levels</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Investigating how the AI system could help prevent surplus food generation in the first place. In conclusion, our Zero Impact AI-Driven Food Redistribution System represents a significant step forward in addressing food waste through smart technology while protecting the environment. The results show that with thoughtful design and implementation, AI can be a powerful tool for sustainability that creates environmental, social, and economic benefits simultaneously</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Expanded</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Applications</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>VII. REFERENCES</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The State of Food and Agriculture 2023: Transforming agrifood systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<pubPlace>Rome, Italy</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">World Food Programme</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Global Report on Food Crises 2024</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Rome, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Climate Change 2024: Mitigation of Climate Change. Contribution of Working Group</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) III to the Sixth Assessment Report of the IPCC," 2024</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between food waste, diet quality, and environmental sustainability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Conrad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Niles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Neher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cleaner Production</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125309</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental impacts of food waste: A global synthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Makov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shepon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Science &amp; Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1294" to="1306"/>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Greenhouse gas emissions from food loss and waste: Updated assessments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">114851</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital platforms in food redistribution: An evaluation framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Goucher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Quested</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Food Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102250</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital transformation in food banks: Opportunities and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonprofit Management and Leadership</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="101"/>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness of digital platforms for urban food waste reduction: A comparative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resources, Conservation and Recycling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning for food surplus prediction in retail environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1143" to="1168"/>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AI-optimized logistics for food distribution: Impacts on emissions and food quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103591</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blockchain-enhanced food donation systems: Impacts on donor participation and food safety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ramos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technology in Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101852</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental impacts of blockchain applications in food supply chains: A critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kouhizadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sarkis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cleaner Production</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">303</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127021</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficiency metrics in food rescue operations: A multi-city analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Hunger &amp; Environmental Nutrition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="163"/>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carbon footprint analysis of food rescue operations in North American cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resources, Conservation and Recycling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">189</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106632</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>